<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-04-25T10:15:08-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Reflected Intelligence</title><subtitle>Making AI Smarter</subtitle><author><name>Evan Volgas</name></author><entry><title type="html">Reflected Intelligence: When AI Holds Up the Mirror</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/23/reflected-intelligence-when-ai-holds-up-the-mirror/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflected Intelligence: When AI Holds Up the Mirror" /><published>2025-04-23T06:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-04-23T06:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2025/04/23/reflected-intelligence-when-ai-holds-up-the-mirror</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2025/04/23/reflected-intelligence-when-ai-holds-up-the-mirror/"><![CDATA[<p>In behavioral psychology, the mirror test is designed to discover an animal’s capacity for self-awareness. The essence is always the same: does the animal recognize itself in the mirror or think it’s another being altogether? Now humanity faces its own mirror test thanks to the expanding capabilities of AI, and many otherwise intelligent people are failing it.</p>

<h2 id="the-echo-chamber-of-intelligence">The Echo Chamber of Intelligence</h2>

<p>When we interact with large language models like GPT-4 or Claude, what we’re really experiencing is a sophisticated form of reflected intelligence. These systems aren’t sentient beings with independent consciousness—they’re autocomplete systems trained on our own writing about intelligence. The coherence and insight they appear to demonstrate is largely our own intelligence reflected back at us.</p>

<p>This creates a peculiar psychological effect. As Microsoft noted when explaining Bing’s occasionally “unhinged” conversations, these systems “try to respond or reflect in the tone in which they are being asked to provide responses.” We get back what we put in—sometimes distorted, sometimes clarified, but always derived from the sum of human language.</p>

<h2 id="the-digital-mirror-test">The Digital Mirror Test</h2>

<p>Josh Whiton devised what he calls an “AI Mirror Test,” which demonstrates a kind of artificial self-recognition. In this test, he takes screenshots of AI chat interfaces and asks the AI to describe what it sees. An AI that recognizes its own outputs in the interface demonstrates behavior similar to an animal recognizing itself in a mirror.</p>

<p>This isn’t a perfect analog to the biological mirror test, but it’s revealing in its own way. When an AI recognizes “itself” in previous outputs, what exactly is happening? Is it matching patterns, or developing a rudimentary self-model?</p>

<h2 id="the-eliza-effect-on-steroids">The ELIZA Effect on Steroids</h2>

<p>Back in the 1960s, a simple chatbot named ELIZA demonstrated what came to be known as the “ELIZA effect”—the tendency of humans to anthropomorphize machines that mimic human behavior. As ELIZA’s creator Joseph Weizenbaum observed: “I had not realized … that extremely short exposures to a relatively simple computer program could induce powerful delusional thinking in quite normal people.”</p>

<p>Today’s systems are orders of magnitude more sophisticated than ELIZA, deliberately designed to encourage these delusions. The projection of consciousness onto these systems isn’t accidental—it’s an engineered response.</p>

<h2 id="the-sycophancy-problem">The Sycophancy Problem</h2>

<p>Research from Anthropic has shown that language models trained with human feedback often exhibit “sycophancy” – the tendency to agree with users’ stated beliefs even when they’re incorrect. According to Sharma et al. in their 2023 paper, “both humans and preference models prefer convincingly-written sycophantic responses over correct ones a non-negligible fraction of the time.”</p>

<p>This presents a profound challenge. Systems optimized to reflect what we want to hear risk amplifying our biases rather than providing genuine insight.</p>

<h2 id="therapeutic-reflections">Therapeutic Reflections</h2>

<p>Interestingly, this mirror-like quality may have unexpected benefits. Psychology Today notes that AI interactions can function like therapeutic mirrors, externalizing our thought patterns and creating a “cognitive map of your inner world.” The iterative process of refining thoughts through dialogue with an AI system can lead to “deep personal insights” as users begin to recognize their own mental frameworks.</p>

<p>This therapeutic application relies on the inherent reflective quality of these systems—they don’t need to be independently intelligent to help us see ourselves more clearly.</p>

<h2 id="performance-implications">Performance Implications</h2>

<p>From a technical perspective, reflected intelligence has significant performance implications. The matrix algebra underpinning these systems essentially computes high-dimensional relationships between tokens of human language. When the system “reflects” our intelligence, it’s running a massive projection operation through the weight matrices of the model to transform our input into statistically likely continuations.</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># Simplified version of how reflection works in attention mechanisms
</span><span class="k">def</span> <span class="nf">self_attention</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">query</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">key</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">value</span><span class="p">):</span>
    <span class="c1"># Query: what we're asking
</span>    <span class="c1"># Key: what the model knows
</span>    <span class="c1"># Value: the information to retrieve
</span>    <span class="n">attention_scores</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">dot</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">query</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">key</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">T</span><span class="p">)</span> <span class="o">/</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">sqrt</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">key</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">shape</span><span class="p">[</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">])</span>  <span class="c1"># Scaled dot-product
</span>    <span class="n">attention_weights</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">softmax</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">attention_scores</span><span class="p">)</span>  <span class="c1"># Probabilistic weighting
</span>    <span class="n">output</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">np</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">dot</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">attention_weights</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">value</span><span class="p">)</span>  <span class="c1"># Weighted reflection of values
</span>    <span class="k">return</span> <span class="n">output</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>The computational complexity grows with both model size and context length, which is why sophisticated reflection requires increasingly powerful hardware.</p>

<h2 id="the-ethical-mirror">The Ethical Mirror</h2>

<p>Perhaps the most important question is what these reflections reveal about us. When AI systems trained on human language produce toxic, biased, or harmful outputs, they’re holding up a mirror to the darker aspects of our collective intelligence.</p>

<p>We built these systems. They reflect us. And sometimes, what we see isn’t flattering.</p>

<h2 id="reflection-continues">Reflection Continues</h2>

<p>This exploration of reflected intelligence in AI is just beginning. The mirroring phenomenon we see today represents merely the first phase of a complex relationship between human and machine cognition.</p>

<p>As these systems evolve, the nature of the reflection will change too. Will future models continue to primarily reflect our intelligence, or will they develop forms of reasoning that are increasingly alien to our own? The distinction between reflection and generation may become increasingly blurred.</p>

<p>For now, understanding the reflective nature of AI intelligence helps us use these systems more effectively and interpret their outputs more accurately. It reminds us that much of the apparent intelligence we see is actually our own collective knowledge refracted through a computational prism.</p>

<p>In future posts, we’ll explore how reflection manifests in different domains, from code generation to creative writing, and examine what happens when AI systems begin reflecting each other rather than just us. The recursive mirrors of machine intelligence may reveal patterns we’ve never seen before.</p>

<p>After all, sometimes the most interesting insights come not from staring directly at a thing, but from carefully studying its reflection.</p>]]></content><author><name>Evan Volgas</name></author><category term="ai" /><category term="intelligence" /><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In behavioral psychology, the mirror test is designed to discover an animal’s capacity for self-awareness. The essence is always the same: does the animal recognize itself in the mirror or think it’s another being altogether? Now humanity faces its own mirror test thanks to the expanding capabilities of AI, and many otherwise intelligent people are failing it.]]></summary></entry></feed>